Hello, everyone.
안녕하세요, 여러분.
Glad to be here.
잘 오셨습니다.
And amazing to see a full house.
만원이라니 놀랍네요.
There are a few seats in the front,
앞쪽에 자리가 몇 개 있어요,
so if you can get some more people,
좀 더 사람을 모을 수 있다면,
there are definitely more seats.
확실히 더 많은 좌석이 있습니다.
But amazing to see everyone here in a full house.
하지만 모두가 꽉 찬 모습을 보니 놀랍습니다.
Shame we can't see the people there on the virtual platform.
가상 플랫폼에서 사람들을 볼 수 없어서 아쉽네요.
I'm really excited to be here at KubeCon.
큐브콘에 오게 되어 정말 기쁩니다.
And today I'd like to talk to you about OpenTelemetry,
오늘은 오픈텔레메트리에 대해 말씀드리겠습니다,
a project that I'm very passionate about, the vision,
제가 매우 열정을 쏟고 있는 프로젝트이자 비전입니다,
the reality, and how to get started with it.
현실, 그리고 그것을 시작하는 방법.
And let's start with a question.
질문부터 시작하겠습니다.
How many tools does a company use, on average,
회사에서 평균적으로 사용하는 도구는 몇 개입니까?
to collect telemetry data from its systems?
시스템에서 텔레메트리 데이터를 수집하는 데 평균적으로 몇 개의 도구를 사용하십니까?
Many.
다수.
Think about logs, metrics, traces.
로그, 메트릭, 트레이스에 대해 생각해 보세요.
Think about your front end app, your back end app,
프론트엔드 앱과 백엔드 앱에 대해 생각해 보세요,
your infrastructure, everything.
인프라, 모든 것을 생각하세요.
How many tools?
도구는 몇 개입니까?
10.
Any other guesses?
다른 추측이 있나요?
Well, recent surveys show that companies
최근 설문 조사에 따르면 기업들은
use, on average, between 5 to 10 different tools
평균적으로 5~10개의 서로 다른 도구를 사용합니다.
to collect telemetry data from the systems.
시스템에서 원격 측정 데이터를 수집합니다.
5 to 10.
5 ~ 10
You can reduce it to one unified standard platform.
하나의 통합된 표준 플랫폼으로 줄일 수 있습니다.
That's the story of OpenTelemetry.
이것이 바로 오픈텔레메트리의 이야기입니다.
I'm Dutan Horvitz.
저는 두탄 호르비츠입니다.
I'm the principal developer advocate at logs.io.
저는 logs.io의 수석 개발자 옹호자입니다.
At logs.io, we provide, essentially,
logs.io에서는 기본적으로 다음과 같은 서비스를 제공합니다,
cloud native observability platform
클라우드 네이티브 통합 가시성 플랫폼
that's based on popular open source tools,
인기 있는 오픈 소스 도구를 기반으로 합니다,
such as Prometheus and Jaeger, and obviously,
프로메테우스나 예거와 같은 유명 오픈소스 툴을 기반으로 합니다,
OpenTelemetry and other projects.
오픈텔레메트리 및 기타 프로젝트.
I'm an advocate of open source and communities in general,
저는 오픈소스와 커뮤니티 전반을 지지합니다,
and the CNCF in particular.
특히 CNCF를 지지합니다.
That's why it's very exciting to be here on the KubeCon stage.
그렇기 때문에 큐브콘 무대에 서는 것이 매우 흥분됩니다.
I co-organize the local CNCF chapter in Tel Aviv.
저는 텔아비브에서 CNCF 지역 지부를 공동 조직하고 있습니다.
I co-organize DevOps days.
데브옵스 데이를 공동 주최합니다.
I have a podcast, Open Observability Talks,
오픈 옵저버빌리티 토크 팟캐스트를 진행합니다,
on open source DevOps and observability.
오픈 소스 데브옵스와 통합 가시성에 대해 이야기합니다.
So if you're a podcast fan, do check it out.
팟캐스트 팬이라면 꼭 들어보세요.
And in general, you can find me everywhere at Horvitz.
그리고 일반적으로 호르비츠의 모든 곳에서 저를 찾을 수 있습니다.
And let's talk about observability.
이제 관찰 가능성에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
As you all know, observability is essentially
모두 아시다시피, 가관측성은 본질적으로
the ability to understand the state of our system
우리 시스템의 상태를 이해하는 능력
based on the telemetry data that it emits.
방출하는 원격 측정 데이터를 기반으로 합니다.
And the vision talks about unified observability
그리고 이 비전은 통합 가시성에 대해 이야기합니다.
across different signal types, classically, the three pillars,
서로 다른 신호 유형에 걸쳐, 고전적으로 세 가지 기둥을 말합니다,
logs, metrics, and traces, but also
로그, 메트릭, 트레이스뿐만 아니라
across different sources.
에 걸쳐 있습니다.
So again, think about your front-end code,
다시 한 번 프런트엔드 코드를 생각해 보세요,
your back-end code, your Kafka-ready,
백엔드 코드, 카프카 지원,
other open source projects, cloud services,
기타 오픈 소스 프로젝트, 클라우드 서비스,
essentially just fusing all of these together
본질적으로 이 모든 것을 융합한 것
to gain insights and observability into your system.
시스템에 대한 인사이트와 관찰력을 확보할 수 있습니다.
That's the vision.
이것이 바로 비전입니다.
The reality, however, is much more fragmented.
하지만 현실은 훨씬 더 파편화되어 있습니다.
And the reason is exactly what we asked at the beginning.
그 이유는 우리가 처음에 질문했던 것과 정확히 일치합니다.
The reason is that we use so many different tools
그 이유는 우리가 너무 다양한 도구를 사용하기 때문입니다.
for observability.
관찰 가능성을 위해.
And each tool and each vendor has its own API and SDK
그리고 각 도구와 공급업체마다 고유한 API와 SDK가 있습니다.
for instrumenting different programming languages,
다양한 프로그래밍 언어를 계측할 수 있습니다,
and then daemon, collector, agent for collecting,
그리고 데몬, 수집기, 수집을 위한 에이전트,
aggregating, processing that data,
집계, 해당 데이터 처리,
and then its own data model and protocol
그리고 자체 데이터 모델과 프로토콜
for transmitting that and sending it over.
전송하고 전송하는 데 사용됩니다.
And all of that is not only an operational headache
이 모든 것은 운영상의 골칫거리일 뿐만 아니라
running so many different tools, but more importantly,
다양한 도구를 실행하는 것도 문제지만 더 중요한 것은
it creates tight coupling between the telemetry collection
원격 측정 컬렉션 간에 긴밀한 결합을 생성합니다.
side and the storage and analytics back end.
측면과 스토리지 및 분석 백엔드 사이에 긴밀하게 연결됩니다.
And most importantly, it makes it very, very difficult
그리고 가장 중요한 것은, 이것이 매우, 매우 어렵게 만든다는 것입니다.
to correlate that data and be able to gain
그 데이터의 상관관계를 파악하여
that unified observability across these essentially data
이러한 본질적인 데이터에 대한 통합 가시성을 확보할 수 있습니다.
silos.
사일로
So that's what open telemetry comes to solve in a nutshell.
이것이 바로 개방형 텔레메트리가 해결하고자 하는 문제입니다.
So open telemetry, or OTEL as its nickname,
그래서 개방형 텔레메트리, 또는 별칭으로 OTEL이라고 합니다,
so if I say OTEL, forgive me, that's
그래서 내가 OTEL이라고 말하면 용서하세요.
how usually the group internally calls it,
그룹 내부에서 일반적으로 부르는 방식입니다,
is an observability framework for generating and capturing,
은 생성 및 캡처를 위한 통합 가시성 프레임워크입니다,
collecting telemetry data from systems, cloud native systems,
시스템, 클라우드 네이티브 시스템에서 원격 측정 데이터를 수집합니다,
across logs, metrics, and traces.
로그, 메트릭 및 추적 전반에서.
So one framework to rule them all if you'd like.
원한다면 하나의 프레임워크로 모든 것을 관리할 수 있습니다.
And it's a project under the CNCF.
그리고 그것은 CNCF의 프로젝트입니다.
It's an incubating project.
인큐베이팅 프로젝트입니다.
It's, in essence, in fact, a merge of open tracing
본질적으로 오픈 트레이싱의 병합입니다.
and open census projects of the CNCF.
CNCF의 오픈 센서스 프로젝트가 합쳐진 것입니다.
So if you're familiar with them, that's the future path.
익숙하다면 앞으로 나아갈 길입니다.
You need to move.
움직여야 해.
That's especially interesting for you this talk.
이번 강연이 특히 흥미롭군요.
And I'm very happy to be here, especially here on the KubeCon
특히 여기 큐브콘에 오게 되어 매우 기쁩니다.
stage, to say that open telemetry has been vastly
개방형 원격 측정이 크게 발전했다고 말할 수 있습니다.
adopted across the industry.
업계 전반에 걸쳐 채택되었습니다.
So you see all the cloud vendors, all the monitoring
모든 클라우드 공급업체와 모든 모니터링이 한 곳에서 이루어집니다.
and observability solutions.
그리고 통합 가시성 솔루션까지.
Everyone has been aligning behind open telemetry,
모두가 개방형 텔레메트리를 지지하고 있습니다,
which is fantastic for us as a community and for the CNCF.
이는 우리 커뮤니티와 CNCF에게 환상적인 일입니다.
It's also the second most active project in the CNCF today.
현재 CNCF에서 두 번째로 활발한 프로젝트이기도 합니다.
In fact, it's the second most active after Kubernetes
실제로 쿠버네티스에 이어 두 번째로 활발합니다.
itself, which is astounding, if you ask me.
그 자체로도 놀랍습니다.
So just to show you how much excitement, how much activity,
얼마나 흥분하고 얼마나 활동적인지 보여드리려고요,
and how much is going goes on in this project.
그리고 이 프로젝트에서 얼마나 많은 일이 진행되고 있는지 보여드리려고요.
And by the way, this is taken from the CNCF DevStats
참고로 이것은 CNCF 개발자 통계에서 가져온 것입니다.
dashboard.
대시보드입니다.
So you can go check it out yourselves
직접 확인해보세요.
and slice and dice the data.
데이터를 잘게 쪼개서 분석해 보세요.
But essentially, it's pretty consistent for a lot of time,
하지만 기본적으로 많은 시간 동안 꽤 일관성이 있습니다,
for a long time already.
이미 오래전부터요.
And I hope that I convinced you that open telemetry is
그리고 제가 오픈 텔레메트리가
interesting and that you are.
흥미롭고 당신은 흥미 롭습니다.
And the reason that this is important,
그리고 이것이 중요한 이유,
because this is how projects become de facto standards.
이것이 프로젝트가 사실상 표준이 되는 방식이기 때문입니다.
When you see the industry aligning behind it,
업계가 그 뒤를 따르는 것을 볼 수 있습니다,
when you see it's very active and moving.
매우 활발하고 움직이는 것을 볼 때.
So I'm really excited, and I truly
그래서 저는 정말 흥분되고, 진심으로
believe that this is going to converge the industry.
이것이 산업을 융합할 것이라고 믿습니다.
And I hope that I managed to convince you, or at least
그리고 제가 여러분을 설득했거나 적어도
that you're interested to hear more.
더 듣고 싶다고 설득했길 바랍니다.
So let's dive deeper into what open telemetry gives us.
이제 개방형 텔레메트리가 제공하는 기능에 대해 자세히 알아봅시다.
So in essence, open telemetry provides us
개방형 텔레메트리는 본질적으로 다음과 같은 이점을 제공합니다.
the APIs, SDKs, and tools for generating telemetry data,
텔레메트리 데이터를 생성하기 위한 API, SDK 및 도구를 제공합니다,
logs, metrics, traces from our own applications.
자체 애플리케이션의 로그, 메트릭, 추적.
And then that's the bluish part on the left-hand side.
그리고 왼쪽의 푸르스름한 부분입니다.
And then a unified way of collecting and processing
그리고 통합된 수집 및 처리 방식입니다.
that data across different sources,
다양한 소스에서 데이터를 수집하고 처리합니다,
both our apps and other types of sources, infrastructure
앱과 다른 유형의 소스, 인프라 모두.
and others.
그리고 기타
And then that's the green part in the middle.
그리고 중간에 녹색 부분이 있습니다.
And then a standard way of exposing and transmitting
그리고 표준 노출 및 전송 방식입니다.
that data, the telemetry data.
그 데이터, 원격 측정 데이터.
That's the orange part.
주황색 부분이죠.
And then sending it off to whichever back end you choose.
그리고 선택한 백엔드로 전송합니다.
Open telemetry does not take any stand in the back end.
개방형 텔레메트리는 백엔드에서 아무런 입장을 취하지 않습니다.
It's your choice.
당신의 선택입니다.
Open telemetry has lots of integrations, as we'll see.
개방형 텔레메트리에는 많은 통합 기능이 있습니다.
It's not part of open telemetry scope.
개방형 텔레메트리 범위에 포함되지 않습니다.
So that's open telemetry in a nutshell.
이것이 바로 개방형 텔레메트리입니다.
And don't worry.
걱정하지 마세요.
I'm going to explain each and every one of these components
이 구성 요소들을 하나하나 설명해드리겠습니다.
in greater detail now.
이제 더 자세히 설명하겠습니다.
But before going into the components,
하지만 컴포넌트로 들어가기 전에,
I'd like to talk a bit about open telemetry specification,
개방형 텔레메트리 사양에 대해 조금 이야기하고 싶습니다,
which is not a component in itself,
그 자체로는 구성 요소가 아닙니다,
but it governs all the other implementations,
하지만 다른 모든 구현에 적용됩니다,
open telemetry implementations out there.
개방형 텔레메트리 구현에 적용됩니다.
And essentially, it provides specification
그리고 기본적으로 다음과 같은 사양을 제공합니다.
to describe cross-language requirements and expectations
언어 간 요구 사항과 기대치를 설명합니다.
across the implementations.
구현 전반에 걸쳐
So it defines the API spec, the SDK spec, and the data spec,
따라서 API 사양, SDK 사양, 데이터 사양을 정의합니다,
things such as semantic conventions, annotations,
의미론적 규칙, 어노테이션 같은 것들을 정의합니다,
and so on, across logs, metrics, and traces.
등, 로그, 메트릭, 추적 전반에서.
And though you won't probably, as end users,
최종 사용자는 아마 느끼지 못하겠지만요,
interact directly with the specification
사양과 직접 상호 작용
on a regular basis as much as the other components,
다른 컴포넌트들처럼 정기적으로 상호작용합니다,
it is important to understand that,
이를 이해하는 것이 중요합니다,
because this comes to solve the exact problem we talked
왜냐하면 이것은 우리가 이야기했던 바로 그 문제를 해결하기 위해서입니다.
about before of fragmentation of each tool and each vendor
각 도구와 각 공급업체의 파편화 이전에 대해 설명합니다.
having its own, and each programming language having
각 프로그래밍 언어가 자체적으로 존재하고, 각 프로그래밍 언어가
its own APIs, SDKs, formats, and so on.
자체 API, SDK, 형식 등이 있습니다.
And moreover, having that across one platform
게다가 하나의 플랫폼에서 이를 모두 사용할 수 있다는 것은
allows then the correlation between the data.
데이터 간의 상관관계를 파악할 수 있습니다.
So it's not just one.
하나만 있는 것이 아닙니다.
It's one that can correlate across signals
신호 간에 상관관계가 있는 신호입니다.
and across sources.
그리고 소스 간에도.
So that's very important to be aware of.
이 점을 알아두는 것이 매우 중요합니다.
And the first component that most people encounter
그리고 대부분의 사람들이 접하는 첫 번째 구성 요소는
are the client libraries.
은 클라이언트 라이브러리입니다.
Open telemetry provides one API and one SDK per language
오픈 텔레메트리는 언어당 하나의 API와 하나의 SDK를 제공합니다.
with which you can instrument and extract logs, metrics,
로그, 메트릭을 계측하고 추출할 수 있습니다,
traces from your application, of course,
물론 애플리케이션의 추적도 가능합니다,
adhering to the specification that we talked about before.
앞서 이야기한 사양을 준수합니다.
It also provides integrations with popular libraries
또한 인기 있는 라이브러리와의 통합을 제공합니다.
and frameworks, RPC, storage, web frameworks, and so on,
프레임워크, RPC, 스토리지, 웹 프레임워크 등과의 통합도 제공합니다,
per language, of course, so that they
물론 언어별로, 그래서
can extract from these languages more information
이 언어에서 더 많은 정보를 추출할 수 있습니다.
and propagate context, and so on, within these frameworks.
이러한 프레임워크 내에서 컨텍스트 등을 전파할 수 있습니다.
And also, auto-instrumentation agents per language,
또한 언어별 자동 인스트루먼트 에이전트도 있습니다,
depending on the languages, that
언어에 따라
allow for a low code to maybe no code instrumentation,
낮은 코드에서 코드 계측이 없을 수도 있습니다,
so that you don't need to modify your code to start extracting
추출을 시작하기 위해 코드를 수정할 필요가 없습니다.
at least table stakes type of metrics and data.
적어도 테이블 스테이크 유형의 메트릭과 데이터입니다.
So essentially, Open Telemetry's mission statement
따라서 본질적으로 Open Telemetry의 사명 선언문은 다음과 같습니다.
is to allow the full range between the fully manual
완전 수동과 완전 수동 사이의 전체 범위를 허용하는 것입니다.
instrumentation to the fully automated instrumentation
계측에서 완전 자동 계측까지
and anything in between.
그리고 그 사이의 모든 것.
And that's important to say anything in between,
그 사이에 있는 모든 것을 말하는 것이 중요합니다,
because you can combine.
결합할 수 있기 때문입니다.
You don't need to decide either or.
둘 중 하나를 결정할 필요가 없습니다.
You can start with auto-instrumentation
자동 인스트루멘테이션으로 시작할 수 있습니다.
to get some table stakes and also lower barrier to entry.
테이블 지분을 확보하고 진입 장벽을 낮출 수 있습니다.
And then you can add, on top of that custom instrumentation,
그리고 그 위에 맞춤형 계기를 추가할 수 있습니다,
to add more fine-grained zoom in areas
를 추가하여 더 세분화된 영역을 확대할 수 있습니다.
that you find important enough.
충분히 중요하다고 생각되는 부분
And also, it accommodates to different situations.
또한 다양한 상황에 적응할 수 있습니다.
If I have something that I can't modify the code,
내가 코드를 수정할 수 없는 것이 있다면,
I need to monitor as black box monitoring,
블랙박스 모니터링으로 모니터링해야 합니다,
because I can't modify, or I'm not allowed to modify,
수정할 수 없거나 수정이 허용되지 않기 때문입니다,
or it's a third party, then, for example,
또는 제삼자이기 때문일 수 있습니다,
auto-instrumentation would be the only option.
자동 인스트루먼트가 유일한 옵션입니다.
It would be a must-have.
꼭 필요한 기능입니다.
So you get the full range of the instrumentation capabilities.
모든 계측 기능을 사용할 수 있습니다.
So that's Open Telemetry Client Libraries.
이것이 바로 개방형 텔레메트리 클라이언트 라이브러리입니다.
Next up, I'd like to talk about Open Telemetry Collector that
다음으로, 오픈 텔레메트리 수집기에 대해 말씀드리겠습니다.
can collect telemetry both from the SDKs
SDK에서 텔레메트리를 수집할 수 있습니다.
that we talked about before, but also from other sources.
뿐만 아니라 다른 소스로부터도 수집할 수 있습니다.
It could collect from infrastructure components,
인프라 구성 요소에서 수집할 수도 있습니다,
open source cloud services.
오픈 소스 클라우드 서비스.
You have a Kafka running.
카프카가 실행 중입니다.
You want to send it.
전송하려고 합니다.
You have a MySQL.
MySQL이 있습니다.
You want AWS or Azure and Google services.
AWS 또는 Azure 및 Google 서비스를 원합니다.
Whatever you can collect, and the Collector
수집할 수 있는 것은 무엇이든, 그리고 수집기
can support that.
가 이를 지원할 수 있습니다.
Process it, aggregate, and then send it
처리하고 집계한 다음 전송합니다.
to whichever back end you choose.
선택한 백엔드로 전송합니다.
And as you could imagine, you can see that here also,
상상할 수 있듯이 여기에서도 볼 수 있습니다,
it's built as a typical data pipeline, data processing
일반적인 데이터 파이프라인, 데이터 처리로 구축되었습니다.
pipeline.
파이프라인.
It has receivers in multiple protocols.
여러 프로토콜의 수신자가 있습니다.
It has processors.
프로세서가 있습니다.
And then it has exporters in multiple protocols.
그리고 여러 프로토콜의 내보내기가 있습니다.
So just as an example, if my code
예를 들어, 내 코드가
emits traces in a Jaeger format, I just
가 예거 형식으로 트레이스를 방출한다면, 저는 그냥
plug in the Jaeger receiver.
예거 수신기를 연결합니다.
If I want metrics from Kafka, I plug in the Kafka receiver,
카프카의 메트릭을 원하면 카프카 리시버를 연결합니다,
and so on and so forth.
등등 등등.
That's for the receivers.
리시버용입니다.
Then the processors have many types of processors
그런 다음 프로세서에는 여러 유형의 프로세서가 있습니다.
to do different types of aggregations and processing,
를 사용하여 다양한 유형의 집계 및 처리를 수행합니다,
batching, filtering, sampling, and so on.
일괄 처리, 필터링, 샘플링 등을 수행합니다.
And I can also chain, concatenate
그리고 체인, 연결도 할 수 있습니다.
different processors to create more elaborate logic.
더 정교한 로직을 만들 수 있습니다.
And then based on the back end analytics tool that I use,
그리고 제가 사용하는 백엔드 분석 도구를 기반으로 합니다,
and it doesn't have to be a single tool.
단일 도구일 필요는 없습니다.
I can use several.
여러 개를 사용할 수 있습니다.
I plug in the relevant exporters.
관련 내보내기를 연결합니다.
If I want to send it to AWS X-Ray,
AWS X-Ray로 보내려면,
I have the receiver for that.
이를 위한 수신기가 있습니다.
I want to send it to Google Pub-Sub.
Google Pub-Sub로 보내고 싶습니다.
I plug it to that.
거기에 연결합니다.
I want to send it to Kafka, to Prometheus, to my company
카프카, 프로메테우스, 내 회사로 보내고 싶어요.
Logs.io as an exporter.
Logs.io를 내보내려고 합니다.
And any vendor and any tool largely supported,
그리고 모든 공급업체와 모든 도구가 대부분 지원됩니다,
you have exporters.
수출업체가 있습니다.
So that's about the collector.
수집가가 있습니다.
And the last component that I would like to talk about
마지막으로 말씀드리고 싶은 구성 요소는 다음과 같습니다.
is the Open Telemetry Protocol, or OTLP.
오픈 텔레메트리 프로토콜, 즉 OTLP입니다.
And OTLP is essentially a general purpose telemetry data
그리고 OTLP는 본질적으로 범용 텔레메트리 데이터입니다.
delivery protocol.
전송 프로토콜입니다.
It can be used, as you can see here,
여기에서 볼 수 있듯이 사용할 수 있습니다,
to send between the SDK, the OTEL SDK to the OTEL collector.
를 사용하여 SDK와 OTEL 수집기 간에 전송할 수 있습니다.
It can be used to send between the collector and the back end
수집기와 백엔드 간에 전송하는 데 사용할 수 있습니다.
analytics tool if it supports it.
분석 도구가 지원하는 경우.
It can be used between intermediary nodes,
중개 노드 간에 사용할 수 있습니다,
such as two different collectors, or any other purpose.
또는 다른 목적으로 사용할 수 있습니다.
It's really a general purpose protocol.
정말 범용 프로토콜입니다.
It's a client server request response.
클라이언트 서버 요청 응답입니다.
As you can see here at the bottom, if you can see,
아래쪽에서 볼 수 있듯이,
it's based on a GRPC and HTTP 1.1 for the transport.
전송을 위한 GRPC와 HTTP 1.1을 기반으로 합니다.
So you have OTLP over HTTP and OTLP over GRPC.
따라서 HTTP를 통한 OTLP와 GRPC를 통한 OTLP가 있습니다.
It currently supports the binary protobuf encoding.
현재 바이너리 프로토부프 인코딩을 지원합니다.
And in the works, there's a plan to support also
그리고 다음 인코딩도 지원할 계획입니다.
JSON encoding over HTTP.
HTTP를 통한 JSON 인코딩.
So you'll have JSON over OTLP over HTTP.
따라서 HTTP를 통한 OTLP를 통한 JSON이 됩니다.
And it's agnostic.
그리고 불가지론적입니다.
So as you can see, you can actually take the proto file,
보시다시피 실제로 프로토 파일을 가져올 수 있습니다,
and you can generate your own GRPC clients yourselves
그리고 여러분만의 GRPC 클라이언트를 직접 생성할 수 있습니다.
if you so choose.
원한다면요.
That's part of the freedom that you have when you use this.
이것이 바로 이 기능을 사용할 때 누릴 수 있는 자유의 일부입니다.
You're not locked into even using these implementations
이러한 구현을 사용하는 것조차도 구속되지 않습니다.
that Open Telemetry provides.
를 사용할 수 있습니다.
It's part of the mindset of Open Telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리의 사고방식의 일부입니다.
Another important point that I would like to make about
제가 말씀드리고 싶은 또 다른 중요한 점은
is that Open Telemetry as a project
프로젝트로서 오픈 텔레메트리가
does not mandate you to use OTLP protocol.
는 OTLP 프로토콜 사용을 의무화하지 않습니다.
As I've shown you just now with the collector,
방금 콜렉터를 통해 보여드렸듯이,
the collector supports many protocols
수집기는 많은 프로토콜을 지원합니다.
for the receivers, for the ingest,
수신기의 경우, 수집기의 경우,
many protocols for the exporters, for the egress.
내보내기, 내보내기를 위한 많은 프로토콜.
So you're not bound to it.
그래서 당신은 그것에 얽매이지 않아요.
However, as a holistic framework aiming
하지만, 전체론적 프레임워크가 지향하는 바는 다음과 같습니다.
to provide a holistic way of generating and collecting
생성하고 수집하는 총체적인 방법을 제공합니다.
telemetry data, the purpose is to get the industry
텔레메트리 데이터, 목적은 업계가
into one unified protocol that can then have also
하나의 통합 프로토콜로 통합하는 것입니다.
the benefit of correlating data.
데이터 상관관계의 이점을 누릴 수 있습니다.
Because if we send logs, metrics, and traces together
로그, 메트릭, 추적을 함께 전송하면 다음과 같은 이점이 있습니다.
with a unified data model, then we
통합 데이터 모델을 사용하면
can also create the correlation, and we
도 상관 관계를 생성할 수 있습니다.
can align the semantic conventions, and so on.
는 의미 규칙을 정렬하는 등의 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
So that's the mindset, and that's the goal.
이것이 마음가짐이고 목표입니다.
And the same goes, by the way, to other components as well.
다른 구성 요소도 마찬가지입니다.
You can use the OTL SDK without the collector, for example,
예를 들어 수집기 없이도 OTL SDK를 사용할 수 있습니다,
sending from the SDK directly to a back end analytics tool.
SDK에서 백엔드 분석 도구로 직접 전송할 수 있습니다.
You can use the collector without an SDK,
SDK 없이 수집기를 사용할 수 있습니다,
like I gave the example of collecting from Kafka directly,
카프카에서 직접 수집하는 예제처럼 말이죠,
and so on.
등등.
So it's a loosely coupled, yet a holistic framework
느슨하게 결합되어 있지만 전체론적인 프레임워크입니다.
aiming to provide a standard, unified way of generating
표준적이고 통일된 생성 방법을 제공하는 것을 목표로 합니다.
and collecting telemetry data.
텔레메트리 데이터를 수집하는 것을 목표로 합니다.
That's about OTLP and maybe the mindset.
OTLP와 마음가짐에 관한 이야기입니다.
These are the main components that I'll cover.
이것이 제가 다룰 주요 구성 요소입니다.
There are other components and other elements.
다른 구성 요소와 다른 요소들이 있습니다.
There's an open telemetry operator
열려 있는 텔레메트리 연산자가 있습니다.
that allows you to install that easily on Kubernetes
쿠버네티스에 쉽게 설치할 수 있다.
and other components.
및 기타 컴포넌트.
But for the sake of this discussion,
하지만 이 논의를 위해,
I will keep it here.
여기 보관하겠습니다.
And now I would like to talk about,
이제 이야기하고 싶어요,
so what's the state of open telemetry project?
오픈 텔레메트리 프로젝트는 어떤 상태인가요?
And most importantly, is that GA?
그리고 가장 중요한 것은, 저게 GA인가요?
Can I use it in production?
프로덕션에서 사용할 수 있나요?
That's the most interesting question, right?
가장 흥미로운 질문이죠?
So show of hands, who thinks yes?
손 들어보시죠, 그렇다고 생각하시는 분?
OK.
좋아요.
And who thinks no?
안 된다고 생각하는 사람?
And who thinks it depends?
그리고 누가 그렇게 생각하죠?
Great.
잘됐네.
So like any interesting question, the answer is,
다른 흥미로운 질문과 마찬가지로 답은 '좋아요'입니다,
it depends.
이다.
And the reason it depends is because open telemetry is,
그 이유는 개방형 텔레메트리가 있기 때문입니다,
in fact, not a monolithic project,
사실 단일화된 프로젝트가 아니기 때문입니다,
but an aggregate of multiple groups,
여러 그룹의 집합체입니다,
and each working on a different part of this huge endeavor.
이 거대한 노력의 각기 다른 부분에서 일하고 있습니다.
So you have the metric standardization specification
메트릭 표준화 사양은 다음과 같습니다.
group, and the tracing one, and the logging one,
그룹, 추적 그룹, 로깅 그룹이 있습니다,
and then you have the Java one, and the .NET one, and the Go
그리고 Java, .NET, Go가 있습니다.
one, and many more.
하나, 그리고 더 많은 것들이 있습니다.
I don't know if there are maintainers here.
여기에 관리자가 있는지 모르겠습니다.
They will probably name 1,000 more.
아마 1,000명이 더 있을 겁니다.
So I'm oversimplifying even that.
그것도 지나치게 단순화했네요.
But just to get the drift, and each SIG,
하지만 드리프트와 각 SIG,
and each special interest group, and each working group,
그리고 각 특별 이익 단체와 각 실무 그룹도요,
and each such component has its own development lifecycle,
그리고 이러한 각 구성 요소에는 고유한 개발 수명 주기가 있습니다,
which means that different parts of open telemetry
즉, 개방형 텔레메트리의 다른 부분은
may be in different state of the maturity lifecycle, which
성숙도 수명 주기의 다른 상태에 있을 수 있습니다.
is, in the CNCF terms, draft, experimental, stable,
은 CNCF 용어로 초안, 실험적, 안정 상태입니다,
and deprecated.
그리고 더 이상 사용되지 않습니다.
Just for those who are more new, we
좀 더 새로운 분들을 위해
have like 67% new people there this year in KubeCon.
올해 큐브콘에는 67%의 새로운 사람들이 참석했습니다.
It's very exciting.
정말 신나는 일이죠.
And just to align the terms with the common terms
그리고 용어들을 일반적인 용어와 일치시키기 위해
in the industry, so stable would be GA, generally available,
업계에서 일반적으로 사용되는 GA가 안정적일 것입니다,
what you'd be looking for to run it in production.
프로덕션에서 실행하려면 무엇을 찾아야 할까요?
And it comes with guarantees, like backwards compatibility,
그리고 이전 버전과의 호환성 같은 보장도 함께 제공됩니다,
and so on.
등등.
Experimental would be beta, so something
실험적은 베타 버전이므로, 뭔가
you can start POCing on, proof of concept.
개념 검증을 시작할 수 있습니다.
So just to align terms.
용어를 정렬합니다.
And again, apologies with the maintainers.
그리고 다시 한번, 관리자들에게 사과드립니다.
I will stick to the common terms just
나는 그냥 일반적인 용어를 고수할 것이다.
to make sure that everyone understands the state.
모든 사람이 상태를 이해할 수 있도록 말이죠.
So OK, we understand that it's complicated.
알았어요, 복잡하다는 건 이해합니다.
Thank you, Dutan.
고마워, 두탄.
But still, what's the state of open telemetry?
하지만 여전히 오픈 텔레메트리의 상태는 어떤가요?
And for that, I'd like to break it down by signal types.
이를 위해 신호 유형별로 세분화해서 살펴보고자 합니다.
And the first signal, and the most mature one, is traces.
첫 번째 신호이자 가장 성숙한 신호는 트레이스입니다.
And open telemetry is generally available for traces
그리고 개방형 텔레메트리는 일반적으로 트레이스에 사용할 수 있습니다.
since last year, which means that the tracing API and SDK
즉, 작년부터 추적 API와 SDK가
and the protocol specifications are stable, the collectors
프로토콜 사양이 안정적이며, 수집기인
table.
테이블.
We have many client libraries, SDK implementations,
많은 클라이언트 라이브러리, SDK 구현이 있습니다,
that are version 1.0 or above.
버전이 1.0 이상입니다.
Version 1.0 is when the tracing implementation is complete.
버전 1.0은 추적 구현이 완료된 경우입니다.
So as you can see here, we have for Java and Go
여기서 볼 수 있듯이 Java와 Go의 경우 다음과 같습니다.
and .NET and Python and C++ and JavaScript and Ruby
그리고 .NET, 파이썬, C++, 자바스크립트, 루비
and Erlang and Swift, and working on more.
그리고 얼랑과 스위프트, 그리고 더 많은 일을 하고 있습니다.
And it keeps on advancing so rapidly
그리고 계속 빠르게 발전하고 있습니다.
that maybe that has even advanced since the last time
어쩌면 지난번보다 더 발전했을지도 모릅니다.
I made the slide.
슬라이드를 만들었습니다.
And most importantly, as I said, GA
그리고 가장 중요한 것은, 제가 말했듯이, GA입니다.
means that it comes with guarantees
은 보증과 함께 제공된다는 것을 의미합니다.
for long-term support, for backwards compatibility,
장기 지원, 이전 버전과의 호환성을 의미합니다,
for dependency isolation, what you'd be expecting
의존성 격리의 경우, 기대할 수 있는 사항
to run it in production.
프로덕션 환경에서 실행하려면.
Next up is metrics.
다음은 메트릭입니다.
And that's actually one of the most exciting news,
가장 흥미로운 소식 중 하나입니다,
at least on the observability front from this KubeCon.
적어도 이번 큐브콘에서 관측성 측면에서는 말이죠.
I'm happy to say, for those who missed the news,
소식을 놓치신 분들을 위해 기쁜 소식을 전합니다,
that metrics has reached the release candidate, just
이 메트릭이 릴리스 후보에 도달했음을 알려드립니다.
the announcement on KubeCon.
에 이르렀습니다.
And release candidate, again, just to align terms,
그리고 릴리스 후보를 다시 릴리스합니다,
means that it's practically GA now collecting
이는 이제 실질적으로 GA가
the feedback from users.
사용자의 피드백을 수집하고 있음을 의미합니다.
And if nothing major critical comes up,
큰 문제가 발생하지 않는다면,
it should be turning the same versions will be turned GA
동일한 버전이 GA로 전환될 것입니다.
within a matter of a week or a couple of weeks more.
일주일 또는 몇 주 더 걸릴 수 있습니다.
That's the time frame.
이것이 시간 프레임입니다.
So the API, the SDK, the protocol are obviously stable.
API, SDK, 프로토콜은 분명히 안정적입니다.
The API and SDK specifications are already
API와 SDK 사양은 이미
implemented in Java and .NET and Python in RC,
Java와 .NET으로 구현되어 있고, RC에서는 Python으로 구현되어 있습니다,
in release candidate.
릴리스 후보에서.
JavaScript is just a week away or something like that.
자바스크립트 출시가 일주일 앞으로 다가왔습니다.
And then many more languages will join in the coming month
다음 달에는 더 많은 언어가 추가될 예정입니다.
or two.
한두 개 정도
In terms of the collector, the collector
수집기 측면에서 보면, 수집기는 다음과 같습니다.
supports metric pipelines.
는 메트릭 파이프라인을 지원합니다.
And very important to say, because as you also
그리고 매우 중요한 것은, 여러분도 아시다시피
heard in the previous talk here in this hall,
여기 이 홀의 이전 강연에서 들으셨죠,
and generally Prometheus being a de facto standard
그리고 일반적으로 프로메테우스는 사실상의 표준입니다.
in the metric side.
미터법 쪽에서.
So there's Prometheus support that
따라서 Prometheus는 다음과 같이 지원합니다.
has been worked on in collaboration
공동 작업 중입니다.
with the Prometheus community.
프로메테우스 커뮤니티와 함께.
I think it's a great example of collaboration under the CNCF.
CNCF에서 협업의 좋은 예라고 생각합니다.
So applause to the teams involved.
참여한 팀들에게 박수를 보냅니다.
And it means that the SDK has exporters in Prometheus format.
SDK에 Prometheus 형식의 익스포터가 있다는 뜻입니다.
The hotel collector has receivers and exporters
호텔 콜렉터에 수신자와 내보내기가 있습니다.
in Prometheus formats, Prometheus remote write.
프로메테우스 형식의 프로메테우스 원격 쓰기.
The OTLP to Prometheus specification is aligned.
OTLP-프로메테우스 사양이 정렬되었습니다.
The data model, so that's there.
데이터 모델이 완성되었습니다.
And the least, I guess, advanced signal
그리고 가장 적은, 아마도 고급 신호
is logs that are still experimental.
은 아직 실험적인 로그입니다.
We hope to have that GA'd this year.
연내 GA를 목표로 하고 있습니다.
And with logging, it's important to understand.
로깅은 이해가 중요합니다.
Logging is the most longstanding signal, obviously.
로깅은 가장 오랜 역사를 지닌 신호입니다.
So everyone has logging.
모든 사람이 로깅을 하고 있군요.
Every system has logging.
모든 시스템에는 로깅이 있습니다.
It's been there for ages.
오래전부터 있었어.
So we can't just ignore that, obviously.
그러니 그냥 무시할 수는 없죠.
So the first focus is to align with existing and support
따라서 첫 번째 초점은 기존 및 지원과 일치하는 것입니다.
existing logging sources and logging systems.
기존 로깅 소스 및 로깅 시스템을 지원하는 것입니다.
And for that, there's also work around the penders,
그리고 이를 위해 펜더를 둘러싼 작업도 있습니다,
log appenders that are under development in many languages.
로그 가산기를 여러 언어로 개발 중입니다.
So that even existing logs that are typically
따라서 일반적으로 다음과 같은 기존 로그도
text-based, unstructured, maybe even file-based,
텍스트 기반, 비정형, 심지어 파일 기반일 수도 있습니다,
can still be augmented with additional data,
여전히 추가 데이터로 보강할 수 있습니다,
such as a trace ID and other important data
추적 ID 및 기타 중요한 데이터 등
to allow correlation.
상관관계를 허용합니다.
And obviously, sending that over OTLP.
그리고 당연히 OTLP를 통해 전송합니다.
So even for existing logging sources,
기존 로깅 소스의 경우에도 마찬가지입니다,
being able to ingest and then model it over OTLP
수집한 다음 OTLP를 통해 모델링할 수 있습니다.
and send it alongside metrics and traces.
메트릭 및 추적과 함께 전송할 수 있습니다.
That's the first priority.
그게 최우선입니다.
But then following up as a holistic framework,
그 다음에는 전체적인 프레임워크로서 후속 조치를 취해야 합니다,
as we talked about the mission statement,
사명 선언문에 대해 이야기했습니다,
we're working to build a new strongly typed and machine
우리는 새로운 강력한 타이핑과 기계를 구축하기 위해 노력하고 있습니다.
readable format also for logs.
로그에도 읽을 수 있는 형식을 만들려고 합니다.
So it's not discarded.
그래서 버려지지 않습니다.
It's definitely the end goal, and to try and converge
확실히 최종 목표이며, 수렴을 시도하는 것입니다.
the industry also around that.
산업을 중심으로요.
And I think the most, if you look at the components,
그리고 구성 요소를 보면 가장 많은 것 같아요,
that for example, you see that the protocol is stable
예를 들어 프로토콜이 안정적이라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
and can send.
전송할 수 있습니다.
That's actually also relatively new news,
이것도 사실 비교적 새로운 소식입니다,
I think less than a week ago.
일주일도 안 된 것 같아요.
We've announced that the OTLP protocol for logs
로그에 대한 OTLP 프로토콜을 발표했습니다.
is already stable and supports the data model that
은 이미 안정적이며 다음과 같은 데이터 모델을 지원합니다.
has been agreed, I think, a month or two ago.
이 한두 달 전에 합의된 것 같습니다.
And the SDK is experimental and can already
그리고 SDK는 실험 중이며 이미
transmit over OTLP.
전송할 수 있습니다.
One thing that is important is that the API, for example,
한 가지 중요한 것은 예를 들어 API입니다,
is left to last.
가 마지막에 남는다는 것입니다.
It's still draft because, again, we
아직 초안이기 때문입니다.
haven't prioritized inventing new APIs for that.
새로운 API를 개발하는 데 우선순위를 두지 않았기 때문입니다.
However, there is now the shift to focus
하지만 이제는 집중하는 방향으로 바뀌고 있습니다.
or adding the focus on the specification side,
또는 사양 쪽에 포커스를 추가합니다,
getting a specification.
사양을 얻습니다.
What does a log, what should the structured, well structured,
로그는 무엇을 구조화해야 하는가?
strongly typed log look like?
강력하게 입력된 로그는 어떤 모습일까요?
And for that, also exciting news from the recent months
그리고 최근 몇 달 동안의 흥미로운 소식도 알려드립니다.
is the collaboration with ECS, Elastic Common Schema,
바로 ECS, Elastic Common Schema와의 협업입니다,
for those who know that.
알고 계신 분들을 위해.
So collaboration between the communities,
커뮤니티 간의 협업,
essentially the open source communities,
본질적으로 오픈소스 커뮤니티입니다,
to get all the aggregated knowledge and work that's
모든 통합된 지식과 작업을 얻을 수 있습니다.
been done around the Elastic Common Schema
Elastic 공통 스키마를 중심으로 수행되었습니다.
and merge it together with open telemetry
오픈 텔레메트리와 함께 병합합니다.
and join forces around that.
이를 중심으로 힘을 합칩니다.
So really exciting news about that as well.
그것도 정말 흥미로운 소식입니다.
So this is about the state.
이건 국가에 관한 것이군요.
And in the bit of time that I have left,
그리고 내게 남은 시간 동안,
I want to first applaud the main achievement here.
우선 여기서 주요 성과에 박수를 보내고 싶습니다.
So let's give her a big round of applause to everyone here.
여기 계신 모든 분들께 큰 박수를 보내주세요.
A lot of hard work.
정말 고생 많았어요.
We have some maintainers here at the audience.
여기 청중석에 관리자가 있습니다.
So we owe them a great deal of gratitude
그래서 우리는 그들에게 큰 빚을 졌습니다.
for achieving this very important milestone.
이 중요한 이정표를 달성한 것에 대해.
Also for those who worked on the logging,
로깅을 위해 애써주신 분들께도 감사드립니다,
as I said, for getting the data and protocol stable.
앞서 말했듯이 데이터와 프로토콜을 안정화하기 위해서입니다.
And for those who are interested in more about the roadmap
그리고 로드맵에 대해 더 궁금하신 분들을 위해
and the future path, it's less the scope of this short talk.
이 짧은 강연에서는 다루지 않겠습니다.
But there was a very interesting maintainers track talk
하지만 매우 흥미로운 메인테이너 트랙 강연이 있었습니다.
by the open telemetry community sharing what's up next,
오픈 텔레메트리 커뮤니티에서 다음 계획을 공유했습니다,
like making the operational side easier,
운영 측면을 더 쉽게 만드는 것과 같은 것들,
like maybe even adding more signals beyond logs, metrics,
로그, 메트릭 외에 더 많은 신호를 추가하는 것과 같은 것들 말이죠,
tracing, discussions around continuous profiling.
추적, 지속적인 프로파일링에 대한 논의.
So if you are interested, do check out
관심이 있으시다면 다음을 확인해 보세요.
the recording from that session, a fascinating session.
그 세션의 녹취록, 아주 흥미로운 세션입니다.
But for the last bit of the talk,
마지막 강연을 위해,
I would like to discuss how to get started with open telemetry.
오픈 텔레메트리를 시작하는 방법에 대해 이야기하고 싶습니다.
And I'd like to offer my bit of advice.
그리고 제 조언을 드리고 싶습니다.
And you should start by knowing your stack.
먼저 자신의 스택을 파악하는 것부터 시작해야 합니다.
You need to figure out the basic four questions.
기본적인 네 가지 질문을 파악해야 합니다.
First, which programming languages
첫째, 어떤 프로그래밍 언어가
does your organization use, especially
조직에서 특히
if you're a polyglot organization, so front end,
다국어 조직인 경우 프런트 엔드입니다,
back end?
백엔드?
Also, which frameworks you use for these?
또한, 어떤 프레임워크를 사용하시나요?
For example, we use Java with Spring,
예를 들어, 우리는 Spring과 함께 Java를 사용합니다,
and we use front end Node.js with Happy and Express.
그리고 Happy 및 Express와 함께 프런트엔드 Node.js를 사용합니다.
So it's important because that will
이것이 중요한 이유는
help you determine which SDKs and agents you can use
사용할 수 있는 SDK와 에이전트를 결정하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
and need to use for your application.
애플리케이션에 사용해야 합니다.
Then, which signals you intend to collect from your system
그런 다음 시스템에서 수집하려는 신호는 다음과 같습니다.
and logs, metrics, traces, and also in which formats, which
로그, 메트릭, 트레이스, 그리고 어떤 형식으로 수집할 것인지도 알려주세요.
is particularly important if it's a brownfield project.
는 재개발 프로젝트의 경우 특히 중요합니다.
You already have components out there
이미 구성 요소가 있습니다.
emitting telemetry traces in Zipkin format,
집킨 형식의 텔레메트리 추적을 방출합니다,
or I don't know what, and you need to adhere to that.
아니면 뭔지 모르겠지만, 그걸 준수해야 합니다.
That will determine the receivers
그러면 수신자가 결정됩니다.
that you will use in the open telemetry collector.
오픈 텔레메트리 수집기에서 사용할 수신기를 결정합니다.
And then, which analytics tools you're
그리고 어떤 분석 도구를 사용 중이신가요?
going to send to in the back end, which will determine,
백엔드에서 어떤 분석 도구로 전송할지 결정합니다,
of course, the exporters that you may want to use.
물론 사용할 수 있는 내보내기가 결정됩니다.
And once you analyze and figure out
그리고 분석하고 파악한 후에는
the stack, your vertical stack that is relevant for you,
스택, 즉 자신과 관련된 수직 스택을 파악합니다,
then just go and check the status
그런 다음 상태를 확인합니다.
of the relevant components and follow the guide.
의 상태를 확인하고 가이드를 따르세요.
And for that, there is a very useful page
이를 위해 매우 유용한 페이지가 있습니다.
that we've set up as part of moving from the sandbox
샌드박스에서 이동하는 과정의 일부로 설정한 페이지가 있습니다.
to the incubation under the CNCF, the opentelemtree.io
CNCF의 인큐베이션으로 이동하기 위해 설정한 오픈스트리트.io를
slash status.
슬래시 상태.
That's a very good starting point
아주 좋은 출발점입니다.
to see the high level status overview.
를 클릭해 높은 수준의 상태 개요를 확인하세요.
There are many other useful resources on that site,
이 사이트에는 다른 유용한 리소스도 많이 있습니다,
like the docs, obviously, and there's also
물론 문서 같은 것도 있고요.
relatively new registry that you can actually
실제로 사용할 수 있는 비교적 새로운 레지스트리
search for your stack.
스택을 검색합니다.
So you realize that you need .net.
.net이 필요하다는 것을 깨닫습니다.
You search .net, and then it will
.net을 검색하면
take you to the specific links on the GitHub repo that
GitHub 리포지토리의 특정 링크로 이동합니다.
pertain to that.
과 관련된 링크입니다.
So it's a really helpful way to navigating
따라서 탐색하는 데 정말 유용한 방법입니다.
around the massive GitHub repo there.
거대한 깃허브 리포지토리를 탐색할 수 있습니다.
I'd also like to invite you to check out the Beginner's Guide
초보자 가이드도 확인해 보세요.
to Open Telemetry that I wrote.
제가 작성한 텔레메트리 열기 가이드도 참고하세요.
It doesn't replace any of what I've shown.
내가 보여준 것을 대체하지 않습니다.
It's just maybe a higher level Beginner's Hello World.
더 높은 수준의 초보자용 헬로 월드일지도 모르겠네요.
So I created a short link so that it's
그래서 짧은 링크를 만들었습니다.
easy to remember, bit.ly-otl-cubecon.
기억하기 쉽도록, bit.ly-otl-cubecon.
And you have the explanation that I
그리고 당신은 내가
said in greater detail about the different components.
다른 구성 요소에 대해 더 자세히 설명했습니다.
It has subguides for different programming languages.
다양한 프로그래밍 언어에 대한 하위 가이드가 있습니다.
Again, just the Hello World, not the deep dive.
다시 말하지만, 헬로 월드만 있고 심층적인 내용은 없습니다.
And also the links to get the deep dive
그리고 심층 분석에 대한 링크도 있습니다.
into the massive data that you have within the open telemetry
오픈 텔레메트리에 있는 방대한 데이터에 대해 자세히 알아보세요.
community.
커뮤니티
So I hope that you find it useful.
도움이 되셨기를 바랍니다.
By the way, if you do have feedback on the guide,
참고로 가이드에 대한 피드백이 있으시다면,
or if you have feedback on this talk,
또는 이 강연에 대한 피드백이 있으시면
or if you have any questions, we're
또는 질문이 있으시다면, 저희는
now going to have a Q&A. So don't go.
이제 Q&A 시간을 갖겠습니다. 그러니 가지 마세요.
We have time for you to ask, and also for the people
여러분도 질문할 시간이 있습니다.
from the virtual platform.
가상 플랫폼에서.
Then feel free to reach out to me also after at Horvitz.
그럼 호르비츠 이후에도 저에게 연락주세요.
And with that, thank you very much.
이것으로 감사합니다.
And don't go.
그리고 가지 마.
Thank you.
고마워요.
If you just raise your hands, we'll pass the microphone
손만 들어주시면 마이크를 넘겨드리겠습니다.
so you can ask questions.
질문하실 수 있습니다.
And for the virtual audience, please
그리고 가상 청중을 위해
write down in the Q&A box in the platform.
플랫폼의 Q&A 상자에 적어주세요.
And we'll also take some questions
그리고 몇 가지 질문도 받겠습니다.
from the virtual platform.
가상 플랫폼에서.
Any question?
질문 있습니까?
Now is the time.
지금이 시간입니다.
We have also maintainers, I think.
우리도 관리자가 있는 것 같아요.
I have spotted a few familiar faces.
낯익은 얼굴들을 몇 명 발견했어.
So you may have the authorities far greater than me.
나보다 훨씬 더 큰 권력을 가지고 있는 것 같군.
If you have specific questions, how is it in Go?
구체적인 질문이 있다면 바둑은 어떤가요?
How is it in .NET?
.NET에서는 어떤가요?
How is that in this exporter, that?
이 내보내기는 어때요?
So you have the right people hanging around here.
여기 제대로 된 사람들이 있군.
Hi.
안녕.
Sorry.
죄송합니다.
On your left.
왼쪽에.
Is there any plans?
계획이 있나요?
Can you stand up?
일어날 수 있겠어?
Sorry, it's difficult to see with the lights.
죄송해요, 불빛 때문에 잘 안 보여요.
Is there any plans to support error tracking as well?
오류 추적 기능도 지원할 계획이 있나요?
Something like Sentry?
센트리 같은 거요?
Error tracking is an interesting part.
오류 추적은 흥미로운 부분입니다.
As I said, currently it's logs, metrics, and traces.
앞서 말했듯이 현재는 로그, 메트릭, 트레이스입니다.
And the next signal that is intended to be,
그리고 다음 신호는 다음과 같습니다,
or now the discussions in early phases of discussion,
또는 이제 논의의 초기 단계에 있습니다,
is the continuous profiling.
은 지속적인 프로파일링입니다.
Things such as ParkHi open source,
파크하이 오픈소스 같은 것들,
if you're familiar with others.
다른 사람들에게 친숙한 경우.
Sentry actually doesn't work that way.
센트리는 실제로 그런 식으로 작동하지 않습니다.
It's based on, how do you call it, snapshots.
스냅샷을 기반으로 합니다.
But ones that are based on, that can be modeled after,
하지만 그 기반이 되는 것들은 모델링할 수 있습니다,
as events similar to logs, it can be converted and then
을 로그와 유사한 이벤트로 변환할 수 있습니다.
relayed over the same mechanism that is built for logs.
로 변환되어 로그와 동일한 메커니즘을 통해 릴레이됩니다.
So it's interesting maybe to explore adapters that
따라서 다음과 같은 어댑터를 살펴보는 것이 흥미로울 수 있습니다.
can actually transform that.
변환할 수 있는 어댑터를 살펴보는 것도 흥미롭습니다.
But I don't know of any specific goal to adhere specifically
하지만 구체적으로 준수해야 할 목표가 있는지는 모르겠습니다.
to these formats.
이 형식에 맞춰야 합니다.
Again, if we have one of the maintainers
다시 말하지만, 메인터너 중 하나에
wanting to have any more detailed information,
더 자세한 정보를 원합니다,
feel free to jump in.
자유롭게 참여하세요.
I hope I answered the question.
질문에 답했으면 좋겠네요.
Thanks.
고마워요.
We've got an online question with a few upvotes,
몇 개의 찬성표를 받은 온라인 질문이 있습니다,
which is, how do things like synthetic monitoring, real user
즉, 어떻게 합성 모니터링, 실제 사용자
monitoring, and application performance monitoring
모니터링, 애플리케이션 성능 모니터링
fit into OpenTelemetry?
오픈텔레메트리에 적합할까요?
So that's an amazing question.
정말 놀라운 질문이네요.
I actually didn't know if I have the time for this talk.
사실 제가 이 이야기를 할 시간이 있는지 몰랐어요.
But if we get it in the Q&A, it's great.
하지만 질의응답을 할 수 있다면 좋겠네요.
Because one of the work that has been started in OpenTelemetry
오픈텔레메트리에서 시작된 작업 중 하나이기 때문입니다.
is a new working group that is dedicated
를 전담하는 새로운 작업 그룹입니다.
to client instrumentation.
클라이언트 계측을 전담하는 새로운 워킹 그룹입니다.
So most of what you see and what you've seen
그래서 당신이 보는 것과 당신이 본 것의 대부분은
is really back end based.
는 실제로 백엔드 기반입니다.
Of course, you can take the existing JavaScript, SDKs,
물론 기존 자바스크립트, SDK를 사용할 수도 있습니다,
and APIs, and you can work it also with client side.
및 API를 사용하여 클라이언트 측에서도 작업할 수 있습니다.
But client side does have its own constraints.
하지만 클라이언트 측에는 고유한 제약이 있습니다.
You need the session ID propagated,
세션 ID가 전파되어야 합니다,
and things like that haven't been
그리고 그런 것들은
modeled into the specification.
사양에 모델링되지 않았습니다.
So there is a new working group for the client instrumentation
클라이언트 계측을 위한 새로운 워킹 그룹이 생겼습니다.
that aims strictly squarely at these use
이러한 용도를 엄격하게 목표로 하는 새로운 워킹 그룹이 있습니다.
instrumenting web pages, web apps, mobile apps, and so on.
웹 페이지, 웹 앱, 모바일 앱 등을 계측합니다.
And so I think this would fit perfectly
그래서 이게 딱 맞는 것 같아요
into both synthetic monitoring and real user monitoring,
합성 모니터링과 실제 사용자 모니터링에 모두 적합합니다,
things that look at your system from outside as a black box.
외부에서 시스템을 블랙박스로 보는 것들.
So if you are interested in that, do get involved.
그러니 관심이 있으시다면 참여해보세요.
Check out this new working group.
이 새로운 워킹 그룹을 확인해 보세요.
It's really in the early phases, so you can actually
아직 초기 단계이므로 실제로는
get involved and influence.
참여하고 영향력을 행사할 수 있습니다.
Do you have more questions from the virtual audience?
가상 청중의 질문이 더 있으신가요?
From the audience here?
여기 방청석에서?
Yeah, another one here is, if we already use Prometheus exporter,
네, 또 하나는 이미 Prometheus 내보내기를 사용하는 경우입니다,
is there a convenient migration path for OpenTelemetry?
오픈텔레메트리를 위한 편리한 마이그레이션 경로가 있나요?
Prometheus exported from the application.
프로메테우스를 애플리케이션에서 내보냈습니다.
So as I said, the OpenTelemetry collector
앞서 말했듯이, OpenTelemetry 수집기가
supports the Prometheus format.
은 프로메테우스 형식을 지원합니다.
So you can actually collect it with the OTL collector,
따라서 실제로 OTL 수집기로 수집할 수 있습니다,
and you can relay that over OTLP.
그리고 OTLP를 통해 전달할 수 있습니다.
So there is a collaboration that
따라서 다음과 같은 협업이 있습니다.
has been done to support Prometheus
프로메테우스를 지원하기 위해 수행되었습니다.
on the collection side.
컬렉션 쪽에서.
As I said, you can also use Prometheus as a back end.
앞서 말했듯이 Prometheus를 백엔드로 사용할 수도 있습니다.
So you can also use a remote write exporter
따라서 원격 쓰기 내보내기를 사용할 수도 있습니다.
to send it to Prometheus as a back end.
를 사용하여 백엔드로 Prometheus로 보낼 수 있습니다.
So you're supported both ways.
양방향으로 지원됩니다.
Any other questions about the future,
미래에 대한 다른 질문이 있으신가요?
where we're heading, ideas?
우리가 나아갈 방향, 아이디어?
So I'm Dutan Horvitz, and thank you very much
저는 두탄 호르비츠입니다, 감사합니다.
for listening, and see you in Kuba.
쿠바에서 뵙겠습니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.